JSON Data:
{
    "title": "Probing the Diversity of Type Ia Supernova Light Curves in the Open Supernova Catalog",
    "author": "Chang Bi, Tyrone E. Woods, S\u00e9bastien Fabbro",
    "subject": "Instrumentation and Methods for Astrophysics (astro-ph.IM); High Energy Astrophysical Phenomena (astro-ph.HE)",
    "comment": "Astrophysical Journal, accepetd",
    "abstract": "The ever-growing sample of observed supernovae enhances our capacity for comprehensive supernova population studies, providing a richer dataset for understanding the diverse characteristics of Type Ia supernovae and possibly that of their progenitors. Here, we present a data-driven analysis of observed Type Ia supernova photometric light curves collected in the Open Supernova Catalog. Where available, we add the environmental information from the host galaxy. We focus on identifying sub-classes of Type Ia supernovae without imposing the pre-defined sub-classes found in the literature to date. To do so, we employ an implicit-rank minimizing autoencoder neural network for developing low-dimensional data representations, providing a compact representation of the supernova light curve diversity. When we analyze light curves alone, we find that one of our resulting latent variables is strongly correlated with redshift, allowing us to approximately ``de-redshift'' the other latent variables describing each event. After doing so, we find that three of our latent variables account for $\\sim$95\\% of the variance in our sample, and provide a natural separation between 91T and 91bg thermonuclear supernovae. Of note, the 02cx subclass is not unambiguously delineated from the 91bg sample in our results, nor do either the over-luminous 91T or the under-luminous 91bg/02cx samples form a clearly distinct population from the broader sample of ``other'' SN Ia events. We identify the physical characteristics of supernova light curves which best distinguish SNe 91T from SNe 91bg \\& 02cx, and discuss prospects for future refinements and applications to other classes of supernovae as well as other transients.",
    "date": "11 Jan 2024"
}
JSON Data:
{
    "title": "Simulation-Based Inference with Neural Posterior Estimation applied to X-ray spectral fitting: Demonstration of working principles down to the Poisson regime",
    "author": "Didier Barret (IRAP, France), Simon Dupourqu\u00e9 (IRAP, France)",
    "subject": "Instrumentation and Methods for Astrophysics (astro-ph.IM); High Energy Astrophysical Phenomena (astro-ph.HE)",
    "comment": "12 pages, 15 figures, submitted to Astronomy and Astrophysics, comments welcome",
    "abstract": "Neural networks are being extensively used for modelling data, especially in the case where no likelihood can be formulated. Although in the case of X-ray spectral fitting, the likelihood is known, we aim to investigate the neural networks ability to recover the model parameters but also their associated uncertainties, and compare its performance with standard X-ray spectral fitting, whether following a frequentist or Bayesian approach. We apply Simulation-Based Inference with Neural Posterior Estimation (SBI-NPE) to X-ray spectra. We train a network with simulated spectra, and then it learns the mapping between the simulated spectra and their parameters and returns the posterior distribution. The model parameters are sampled from a predefined prior distribution. To maximize the efficiency of the training of the neural network, yet limiting the size of the training sample to speed up the inference, we introduce a way to reduce the range of the priors, either through a classifier or a coarse and quick inference of one or multiple observations. SBI-NPE is demonstrated to work equally well as standard X-ray spectral fitting, both in the Gaussian and Poisson regimes, both on simulated and real data, yielding fully consistent results in terms of best fit parameters and posterior distributions. The inference time is comparable to or smaller than the one needed for Bayesian inference. On the other hand, once properly trained, an amortized SBI-NPE network generates the posterior distributions in no time. We show that SBI-NPE is less sensitive to local minima trapping than standard fit statistic minimization techniques. We find that the neural network can be trained equally well on dimension-reduced spectra, via a Principal Component Decomposition, leading to a shorter inference time. Neural posterior estimation thus adds up as a complementary tool for X-ray spectral fitting. (abridged).",
    "date": "11 Jan 2024"
}


Tokenization --> Stopwords removal --> Lemmatization

"ever-growing sample observed supernova enhances capacity comprehensive supernova population study providing richer dataset understanding diverse characteristic Type Ia supernova possibly progenitor present data-driven analysis observed Type Ia supernova photometric light curve collected Open Supernova Catalog available add environmental information host galaxy focus identifying sub-classes Type Ia supernova without imposing pre-defined sub-classes found literature date employ implicit-rank minimizing autoencoder neural network developing low-dimensional data representation providing compact representation supernova light curve diversity analyze light curve alone find one resulting latent variable strongly correlated redshift allowing u approximately `` de-redshift '' latent variable describing event find three latent variable account \\sim 95\\ variance sample provide natural separation 91T 91bg thermonuclear supernova note 02cx subclass unambiguously delineated 91bg sample result either over-luminous 91T under-luminous 91bg/02cx sample form clearly distinct population broader sample `` '' SN Ia event identify physical characteristic supernova light curve best distinguish SNe 91T SNe 91bg 02cx discus prospect future refinement application class supernova well transient"

"Neural network extensively used modelling data especially case likelihood formulated Although case X-ray spectral fitting likelihood known aim investigate neural network ability recover model parameter also associated uncertainty compare performance standard X-ray spectral fitting whether following frequentist Bayesian approach apply Simulation-Based Inference Neural Posterior Estimation SBI-NPE X-ray spectrum train network simulated spectrum learns mapping simulated spectrum parameter return posterior distribution model parameter sampled predefined prior distribution maximize efficiency training neural network yet limiting size training sample speed inference introduce way reduce range prior either classifier coarse quick inference one multiple observation SBI-NPE demonstrated work equally well standard X-ray spectral fitting Gaussian Poisson regime simulated real data yielding fully consistent result term best fit parameter posterior distribution inference time comparable smaller one needed Bayesian inference hand properly trained amortized SBI-NPE network generates posterior distribution time show SBI-NPE le sensitive local minimum trapping standard fit statistic minimization technique find neural network trained equally well dimension-reduced spectrum via Principal Component Decomposition leading shorter inference time Neural posterior estimation thus add complementary tool X-ray spectral fitting abridged"
