JSON Data:
{
    "title": "Probing the Diversity of Type Ia Supernova Light Curves in the Open Supernova Catalog",
    "author": "Chang Bi, Tyrone E. Woods, S\u00e9bastien Fabbro",
    "subject": "Instrumentation and Methods for Astrophysics (astro-ph.IM); High Energy Astrophysical Phenomena (astro-ph.HE)",
    "comment": "Astrophysical Journal, accepetd",
    "abstract": "The ever-growing sample of observed supernovae enhances our capacity for comprehensive supernova population studies, providing a richer dataset for understanding the diverse characteristics of Type Ia supernovae and possibly that of their progenitors. Here, we present a data-driven analysis of observed Type Ia supernova photometric light curves collected in the Open Supernova Catalog. Where available, we add the environmental information from the host galaxy. We focus on identifying sub-classes of Type Ia supernovae without imposing the pre-defined sub-classes found in the literature to date. To do so, we employ an implicit-rank minimizing autoencoder neural network for developing low-dimensional data representations, providing a compact representation of the supernova light curve diversity. When we analyze light curves alone, we find that one of our resulting latent variables is strongly correlated with redshift, allowing us to approximately ``de-redshift'' the other latent variables describing each event. After doing so, we find that three of our latent variables account for $\\sim$95\\% of the variance in our sample, and provide a natural separation between 91T and 91bg thermonuclear supernovae. Of note, the 02cx subclass is not unambiguously delineated from the 91bg sample in our results, nor do either the over-luminous 91T or the under-luminous 91bg/02cx samples form a clearly distinct population from the broader sample of ``other'' SN Ia events. We identify the physical characteristics of supernova light curves which best distinguish SNe 91T from SNe 91bg \\& 02cx, and discuss prospects for future refinements and applications to other classes of supernovae as well as other transients.",
    "date": "11 Jan 2024"
}
JSON Data:
{
    "title": "Simulation-Based Inference with Neural Posterior Estimation applied to X-ray spectral fitting: Demonstration of working principles down to the Poisson regime",
    "author": "Didier Barret (IRAP, France), Simon Dupourqu\u00e9 (IRAP, France)",
    "subject": "Instrumentation and Methods for Astrophysics (astro-ph.IM); High Energy Astrophysical Phenomena (astro-ph.HE)",
    "comment": "12 pages, 15 figures, submitted to Astronomy and Astrophysics, comments welcome",
    "abstract": "Neural networks are being extensively used for modelling data, especially in the case where no likelihood can be formulated. Although in the case of X-ray spectral fitting, the likelihood is known, we aim to investigate the neural networks ability to recover the model parameters but also their associated uncertainties, and compare its performance with standard X-ray spectral fitting, whether following a frequentist or Bayesian approach. We apply Simulation-Based Inference with Neural Posterior Estimation (SBI-NPE) to X-ray spectra. We train a network with simulated spectra, and then it learns the mapping between the simulated spectra and their parameters and returns the posterior distribution. The model parameters are sampled from a predefined prior distribution. To maximize the efficiency of the training of the neural network, yet limiting the size of the training sample to speed up the inference, we introduce a way to reduce the range of the priors, either through a classifier or a coarse and quick inference of one or multiple observations. SBI-NPE is demonstrated to work equally well as standard X-ray spectral fitting, both in the Gaussian and Poisson regimes, both on simulated and real data, yielding fully consistent results in terms of best fit parameters and posterior distributions. The inference time is comparable to or smaller than the one needed for Bayesian inference. On the other hand, once properly trained, an amortized SBI-NPE network generates the posterior distributions in no time. We show that SBI-NPE is less sensitive to local minima trapping than standard fit statistic minimization techniques. We find that the neural network can be trained equally well on dimension-reduced spectra, via a Principal Component Decomposition, leading to a shorter inference time. Neural posterior estimation thus adds up as a complementary tool for X-ray spectral fitting. (abridged).",
    "date": "11 Jan 2024"
}
JSON Data:
"ever-grow sampl observ supernova enhanc capac comprehens supernova popul studi provid richer dataset understand divers characterist type ia supernova possibl progenitor present data-driven analysi observ type ia supernova photometr light curv collect open supernova catalog avail add environment inform host galaxi focu identifi sub-class type ia supernova without impos pre-defin sub-class found literatur date employ implicit-rank minim autoencod neural network develop low-dimension data represent provid compact represent supernova light curv divers analyz light curv alon find one result latent variabl strongli correl redshift allow us approxim `` de-redshift '' latent variabl describ event find three latent variabl account \\sim 95\\ varianc sampl provid natur separ 91t 91bg thermonuclear supernova note 02cx subclass unambigu delin 91bg sampl result either over-lumin 91t under-lumin 91bg/02cx sampl form clearli distinct popul broader sampl `` '' sn ia event identifi physic characterist supernova light curv best distinguish sne 91t sne 91bg 02cx discuss prospect futur refin applic class supernova well transient"
JSON Data:
"neural network extens use model data especi case likelihood formul although case x-ray spectral fit likelihood known aim investig neural network abil recov model paramet also associ uncertainti compar perform standard x-ray spectral fit whether follow frequentist bayesian approach appli simulation-bas infer neural posterior estim sbi-np x-ray spectra train network simul spectra learn map simul spectra paramet return posterior distribut model paramet sampl predefin prior distribut maxim effici train neural network yet limit size train sampl speed infer introduc way reduc rang prior either classifi coars quick infer one multipl observ sbi-np demonstr work equal well standard x-ray spectral fit gaussian poisson regim simul real data yield fulli consist result term best fit paramet posterior distribut infer time compar smaller one need bayesian infer hand onc properli train amort sbi-np network gener posterior distribut time show sbi-np less sensit local minima trap standard fit statist minim techniqu find neural network train equal well dimension-reduc spectra via princip compon decomposit lead shorter infer time neural posterior estim thu add complementari tool x-ray spectral fit abridg"
